חודש טוב *Chodesh Tov*, today's דף daf, *Daf* is טז *Tet Zayin*,
we pick up in the middle of טו עמוד ב *Tet Vav
Amud Bet*. We're going through the list of things which are practices
for an אבל avel *Avel* and then possibly I guess the same
practices by מצורע metzora *Metzora* and מנודה menude, *Menudeh*, mostly yes, some
not.
And we pick up with the
and the last one we left with was whether רחיצה rechitza *Rechitzah*,
where there was not clear evidence one way or the other that
application to מצורע metzora, *Metzora* and מנודה menude? *Menudeh*. Now we pick
up four lines before the lines get wide. אבל avel, אסור בנעילת
הסנדל *Avel assur bine'ilat hasandal*, an אבל avel *Avel* is not allowed
to wear a shoe. מנא לן דאמר רחמנא ליחזקאל *Mina lan de'amar
Rachmana leYechezkel* ונעליך תשים ברגליך *u'na'alecha tasim beraglecha*, God says to יחזקאל
Yechezkel, *Yechezkel* put your shoes on your feet. So again, this being
one of the cases where we say we the יחזקאל Yechezkel. *Yechezkel*
do the opposite of what the practice is for. So therefore מכלל
דכולי עלמא אסור *Miklal d'chulei alma assur*, from that we can infer
that the normal rule is that it is forbidden. מנודה menude מהו
בנעילת הסנדל
*Menudeh ma'u bine'ilat hasandal*? How about a מנודה menude *Menudeh*? What's that
story with wearing a shoe? אמר רב יוסף Amar Rav Yosef, תא
שמע tashma *Amar Rav Yosef tashma*, come hear, כשאמרו אסור בנעילת הסנדל
*Keshe'amru assur bine'ilat hasandal*, when they said this is again going back
to the practices of a תענית *Taanit*, thank you so much, when
they said you cannot you cannot wear a סנדל *Sandal*, a shoe,
לא אמרו אלא בעיר *Lo amru ela be'ir*, they only said in
the city, אבל avel בדרך מותר *Aval baderech mutar*, but if somebody
is traveling on the way, so מותר *Mutar* is permissible. הא כיצד
*Ha keitzad* in the context of a תענית *Taanit*? יצא לדרך נועל
*Yatza laderech no'el*, when somebody goes out to start a journey he
puts on his shoe. נכנס לעיר חולץ *Nichnas la'ir choletz*, when he
enters into the city he removes the shoe. Okay, so that's interesting
about the shoe, but what does it tell us about our question?
וכן אתה מוצא במנודה ובאבל *Vechen atta motzeh bemenudeh u've'avel*, and you
find that the same is true by somebody who is in נידוי
niduy *Nidduy* and somebody who is an אבל avel *Avel*. So it
seems very clear that the practice of not wearing a shoe applies
to מנודה menude *Menudeh*. So this is again the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*,
a constant refrain, that all these practices by תענית *Taanit* it says
and the same by מנודה menude *Menudeh* and אבל avel *Avel*. So
on the face of it it seems pretty good evidence that the
same practices apply, but then the גמרא Gmara *Gemara* is going to
have its ready response. מאי לאו אכולהו *Mai lav a'kulehu*? When it
says similar practices are by a מנודה menude. *Menudeh* and an אבל
avel, *Avel*, presumably it means all of these practices, meaning also most
likely the one just mentioned about the not wearing of the shoe.
And that's the same practice by מנודה menude? *Menudeh* and אבל avel.
*Avel*? So the גמרא Gmara *Gemara* says לא אשארא *Lo a'shara*, no,
it's saying that there are other practices that a that done on
a תענית *Taanit* that are the same by מנודה menude, *Menudeh* and
אבל avel. *Avel*. You know, like not bathing or actually bathing was
the one we asked about, not getting, you know, you know, not
getting a haircut, other types of practices that are the same, but
not necessarily the one just mentioned. Okay, so although on the face
of it it seems like a מנודה menudeh *Menudeh* does not wear
shoes, the גמרא Gmara *Gemara* sort of says it's not absolutely approved.
And it doesn't answer the question. מצורע metzora? מהו בנעילת הסנדל *Metzora
ma'u bine'ilat hasandal*, what's the story about a מצורע metzora. *Metzora* by
wearing a shoe? תיקו *Teiku*, that is unanswered. So, you know, which
raises then together with רחיצה *Rechitzah*, again the simple sense of רחיצה
*Rechitzah* is that it's in the only for this category things that
are only for the אבל avel *Avel*. So the simple sense by
רחיצה *Rechitzah* was that it applied by מנודה menudeh *Menudeh* because you
had the same line yesterday by רחיצה *Rechitzah*, right? It said וכן
אתה מוצא *Vechen atta motzeh*. So the simple sense is that רחיצה
*Rechitzah* and נעילת הסנדל *Ne'ilat hasandal*
do apply by מנודה menudeh *Menudeh* and מצורע metzora? *Metzora* as well,
but it is not the גמרא Gmara *Gemara* does not come out
to a clear proof about them. Again, so the simple sense is
that they do apply and certainly by נעילת הסנדל *Ne'ilat hasandal* you
can understand that sense of sort of like, you know, cast out
from the community, again one of these things about physical appearance and
walking around, hair growing wild, clothes disheveled, shoes off is all part
of that sort of being, you know, cast out of society type
of way of appearance. The ones that are again that are most
clear that are distinct by an אבל ovel *Avel* are תפילין tefillin
*Tefillin* and תורה Torah, *Torah*, which have to do with that embracing,
you know, the joy of תורה Torah *Torah* or the glory and
that affirmation aspects of it, you know. And כפיית המיטה *Kefiyat hamittah*,
which is very unique to אבל ovel. *Avel*. And the once and
the final thing which might have one assumed was over here is
עשיית מלאכה *Asiyat melachah*. But remember, עשיית מלאכה *Asiyat melachah* is not
in terms of, you know, it's forbidden even if it's not interacting
with other people. עשיית מלאכה *Asiyat melachah* is even on your own
and that really has less to do with the societal aspect and
more to do with what the גמרא Gmara *Gemara* in elsewhere identifies
עשיית מלאכה *Asiyat melachah* to be as מסיח דעת מן האבילות *Mesiach
da'at min ha'aveilus*, as an issue of again just, you know, the
focus on the interior state. It is ironic or it is unexpected
I should say that remember one of the things we said by
מנודה menudeh *Menudeh* was that not only can he do his own
מלאכה *Melachah*, but he can actually hire laborers and be hired out
and so on. So a מנודה menudeh. *Menudeh* is not fully cut
off from society in that way.
Yes, I know you explained it yesterday what's the connection between כפיית
המיטה *Kefiyat hamittah* and the... the visage of the person's
face or the person's image?
Yeah, I didn't explain it yesterday. I mean, you know, there's some
sense about the about things being turned upside down, but, yeah, but
I don't exactly understand the specific connection. What?
The divine image or something?
Yeah. Yeah, but the question is what's the relationship of of the
bed to the divine image. All right. So now the גמרא Gemara
continues. Okay. So where are we?
yes,
this outcast idea. Yeah, and maybe this is the wrong time to
discuss this. The אבל ovel. and the מצורע metzora. and the
מנודה, menudeh. I don't know, are people who are in a circumstance
not of their own choosing. Right. Right. The אבל, ovel why
the idea of being outcast?
Well, outcast is the wrong word because outcast means that the society
has cast you out,
separate separated from society. You know, the אבל Aveil, is not, you
know, his idea is that he is that, you know, I think,
you know, you could try to explain this all במקרא, bemikra, and
all of these by the אבל have nothing to do with the
separated from society, just have to do with an expression of that
sense of, you know, mourning and sadness and so on. But I
think that it's not, I think it's not במקרא. bemikra. I think
the idea, I mean, if you think about, think about just for
a minute the idea of the שבעה, shiva, not leaving the house,
right? So that's basically that idea that this person is not in
a state right now where they have are, you know, have that
normal type of embeddedness, interactions with society. They're separated out in order
to focus on their what, you know, what's going on there on
their status of on their state of mourning and on what's and,
you know, to be consoled but also to be reflective and to
allow themselves to, you know, to fully, what's word, assimilate, you know,
the reality of what has occurred, not to go on with life
as usual. So I don't, outcast is the wrong word, but sort
of separated out from society is I think the point. Now the
מצורע, metzora, why they should be that way, but that's certainly the
message in the תורה, Torah right? טמא טמא יקרא, tamei tamei yikra,
בגדיו יהיו פרמים, bigadav yihyu phrumim, you know, it's sort of like
it's clearly like stay away. But you're right, it's not by by
the אבל everybody's supposed to come to him and be מנחם אבלים,
menachem avelim, right? So it's not about, but it's still about not
being engaged in the normal rhythms of life, right? And the normal
types of rhythms, that's that's the way I see it, but you're
right, it's outcast would not be the right word. The מנודה? menudeh
The מנודה menudeh is exactly that, is that this person has acted
in in unacceptable ways and it's sort of a way of societal
censure and sort of and sort of and, you know, so there
is something excommunication, although מנודה menudeh is not, that's חרם, cherem, this
is a lesser degree, but that's...
This person's acted in an unacceptable way and so then and then
so the הלכה halacha then demands of them to act in additional
antisocial behavior.
Right. Well, right, meaning to some degree it's how we behave with
him, but it is interesting that most of the demands of the
מנודה menudeh is how the מנודה menudeh has to act, you know,
himself. But right, but is exactly, he has to own that and
we have to give him the societal cold shoulder, right? Until he's
ready to act in a way that's acceptable for the socially acceptable
and then there's like, you know, religiously and, you know, and otherwise
acceptable. What he did wrong was not that he was not that
he wore smelly clothes, I mean, he's being cast out not because
he did things that were socially unacceptable by society, right, yeah.
And now you're telling him to wear smelly clothes. Right. I wonder
about that compliance rate with...
I have no idea. I have no idea.
We we forget that we always wear clean clothes. That has not
been the norm of societies ever.
Okay, but torn clothes, wild hair, all of this is to act
in socially unacceptable ways. But yes, and it's but it's because he
acted in ways that were more like a in terms of more
significant practices, religious practices, otherwise unacceptable. We'll see actually in the rest
of today's when we get to the actual today's דף, daf the
reason the person does become a מנודה. menudeh Okay, so let's take
a look. The גמרא Gemara, continues.
Okay.
אבל אסור בתשמיש המיטה, avel asur betashmish hamita, an אבל can't have
sex, דכתיב, d'chtiv, וינחם דוד את בת שבע אשתו, vayenachem David et
Batsheva ishto, David consoled Batsheva and he came unto her, meaning they
had sex, when that was after the אבלות avelus for the for
the infant completed. So מכלל דמעיקרא אסור, miklal d'me'ikara asur, so the
context of the verse makes it sound like that wasn't במקרה, bemikreh,
it was because the אבלות avelus was completed. So shows you as
a general rule it's forbidden. So מנודה מהו בתשמיש המיטה? menude mahu
betashmish hamita? What's the story with a מנודה? menudeh? אמר רב יוסף,
תא שמע כל אותן שנים שהיו ישראל במדבר מנודין היו, Amar Rav
Yosef tashma kol osan shanim shehayu Yisrael bamidbar menudin hayu, all those
years that ישראל Yisrael were in the מדבר, midbar, those 38 years,
they were מנודה, Menudah. right? God had sort of like rejected them,
ושימשו מיטותיהם veshimshu mitotayhem and they had sex because you can tell
because they had kids. So you see it's allowed. אמר ליה אביי,
Amar lay Abaye, so אביי Abaye said back, דדילמא מנודה לשמים שאני
d'dilma menude lashamayim shani דקיל, d'kil, maybe that was different, maybe that
was
they were... More lenient? דאמרת חמיר, da'amarta chamir, a minute ago you
said by yesterday's דף Daf, that you can't prove things by the
status of being מנודה לשמים menudeh lashamayim because maybe that's weightier to
be מנודה לשמים, menudeh lashamayim, which makes sense. So the גמרא Gemara
says, ספוקי מספקא ליה, sefuki mesapka lei, he doesn't know whether the,
how to treat the status of מנודה לשמים. menudeh lashamayim. So זיל
הכא קמדחי ליה וזיל הכא קמדחי ליה, zeil hacha kamidachi lei vezeil
hacha kamidachi lei, you go here he'll push you away, you go
there he'll push you away, meaning he tried to, he challenges any
proof from the case of מנודה לשמים menudeh lashamayim saying maybe those
cases are more lenient, maybe those cases are more strict, we don't
know whether that's exactly comparable to מנודה לבריות, menudeh labriyot, which is
quite fascinating, the idea of that rejected by people has weightier consequences
than like, you know, rejected by heaven.
So, you know, I don't exactly know how to fully explain that
except the fact that if the practices are about, you know, being
outside of society, so the fact that your behavior was found unacceptable,
you know, to the society might actually translate into harsher types of
practices, you know, than in the terms of your relationship to God.
Your relationship to God could have other consequences, but נידוי niduy as
an expression of your relationship to society maybe is even more strict
when you're מנודה Menuday. to society than מנודה Menuday to God. So
the גמרא Gemara does not really conclude that. So now it says,
how about מצורע? metzora Yeah, let's just read the, finish the idea
of מצורע. metzora So the גמרא Gemara says, מצורע מהו בתשמיש המיטה?
metzora mahu betashmish hamitah? How about a מצורע? metzora? תא שמע דתניא,
ta shema detanya, וישב מחוץ לאוהלו, veyashav michutz le'ahalo,
he shall sit outside his tent, כבי מנודה וחבר ואסור בתשמיש המיטה,
kebei menudeh vechaver ve'assur betashmish hamitah, he should be like a מנודה
and a חבר chaver and is forbidden to have sex. So you
see ואין אהלו אלא אשתו, ve'ein ohalo ela ishto, and his tent
means his wife, שנאמר, shenemar, לכו אמרו להם שובו לכם לאהליכם, lechu
imru lahem shuvu lachem le'ohaleichem, tells them go back to their wives
after הר סיני Har Sinai and that was after it says אל
תגשו אל אשה. al tigshu el ishah. Of course all of this
is focused on the male from the male's perspective, but anyway it
means to be intimate with one's wife from the male's man's perspective.
So שמע מינה, shma mina, so you see that's clear in the
verse that he is forbidden to his wife. So well right, that
is the question which the גמרא Gemara is glossing over here, that
it might only be ironically as he's becoming טהור. tahor. We had
that whole discussion earlier. But anyway at least you have that concept
by מצורע. metzora? ונפשוט נמי למנודה, venifshot nami lemenudeh, also learn it
out to מנודה because it says he's like a מנודה. So אמר
רב הונא בריה דרב פנחס משמיה דרב יוסף, amar Rav Huna brei
deRav Pinchas mishmei deRav Yosef,
מי קתני שאסור? mi katani she'assur? Again, it doesn't say explicitly he's
forbidden in sex like a מנודה. שיהא כמנודה וחבר sheyehei kemenudeh vechaver
and an אבל, it says he's forbidden in sex and he should
be like a מנודה and an אבל. Maybe not in sex, maybe
in the other
areas, במילי אחרנייתא, bemilei achrayita, in other areas. ואסור נמי בתשמיש המיטה,
ve'assur nami betashmish hamitah, he's also forbidden in sex, but maybe that's
not the way that's not the way we're comparing him to מנודה
and an אבל. So again, it's not clear, but the simple sense
here is that תשמיש המיטה tashmish hamitah is on this side, okay,
and the interesting thing is that that is something that is not
really about, you know, the broader society. That is a man or
a woman's own intimate home life and there's no idea like that
somebody is מנודה that his wife isn't supposed to talk to him
or his her husband isn't supposed to talk to her. So the
fact that this is, I mean again, the גמרא Gemara doesn't know
for sure by מנודה to clear by מצורע, metzora but you know,
but it does sort of the simple evidence is that it's here.
You know, that I will admit that raises challenges to my sort
of category, you know, because this is something that I think again
you could say maybe not, maybe there's an idea that even in
your home life you're supposed to feel detached and separated and so
on. But it does seem more here that there is this idea
of just of questions about like a pleasure, and that also might
get to the רחיצה aspect, you know, and maybe there are aspects
of the מנודה and the מצורע metzora that are about just, you
know, certain things that are, you know, a certain type of a
physical
engage... physical pleasure that it's supposed to be not that is inappropriate.
Again by the אבל you can understand it easier if it's supposed
to be about a sense of sadness and bitterness and so on,
there's simply a certain type of, you know, of indulging in certain
pleasures. By the מנודה and the מצורע metzora, again, you can say
everything oh it's a form of punishment, you're in נידוי niduy. so
you have to suffer, so this is a way of suffering because
you're in נידוי. Niddui But the nice distinctions that I was trying
to lay out yesterday, I will admit become a little bit more
in my mind questionable once we start putting תשמיש המיטה tashmish hamitah
on this side of it. That's like the most private thing. Think
about the fact that on שבת Shabbat and רגל Regel דברים שבצנעא
נוהג devarim shebetzina noheig and what is that? You still don't have
sex, it's דברים שבצנעא, devarim shebetzina, it's total form of practicing of
אבילות aveilut that is completely, you know, hidden from society, whether a
person is or is not doing it. So I think that that
does for me raise the quest... raise questions about my the simple
sort of division that I was putting out there yesterday. You had
a question though.
Yeah, הלכתית halachitit is נידוי בידי שמים niduy bidei shamayim more חמור
chamur or less חמור chamur than בידי אדם? bidei adam?
Well that's what I was thinking about.
Yeah, it's a...
like if a חטא cheit that has a מיתה בידי שמים mitah
bidei shamayim considered to be... let me let me frame it this
way. Why? No, we're almost done. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this.
Okay. Okay.
אבל אינו משלח קרבנותיו, Ovel eino meshale'ach korbanosav, and an אבל cannot
send קרבנות korbanos to be brought for him in the בית המקדש,
Beis Hamikdash, דתניא רבי שמעון אומר שלמים, detanya Rabbi Shimon omer shlamim,
it's they're called the שלמים, shlamim, בזמן שהוא שלם, bizman shehu shaleim,
when he is in a sense of completeness, ולא בזמן שהוא אונן,
velo bizman shehu onen, not when he is an אונן. onen. And
again, ignoring the difference between אונן onen and אבל. But now, of
course, by אונן onen that particularly fits. אונן Onen isn't doing מצות,
mitzvos, there's a sense of sort of existential distance from God during
that period. And that fits very well. You know, even in the
אבלות aveilus sense, you know, even if you do מצות, mitzvos, the
more perhaps like intimate aspect and affirmative aspect, you know, it does
somewhat fit into the תפילין and תורה Torah type of an idea
there by the אבל. So that's קרבנות, korbanos, so that's that. מנודה
מהו שישלח קרבנותיו? Menudeh mahu sheyishale'ach korbanosav? How about a מנודה? אמר
רב Rav יוסף תא שמע tashma, כל אותן שנים שהיו ישראל במדבר
kol otan shanim shehayu Yisrael bamidbar מנודין היו, menudin hayu, the years
that ישראל Yisrael were in the מדבר midbar they were מנודין, menudin,
ושלחו קרבנותיהם, veshalechu korbanoseihem, and they brought קרבנות. korbanos. There's no evidence
they didn't bring קרבנות korbanos during that entire period. אמר ליה אביי,
Amar lei Abaye, it's not explicit but presumably they did. אמר ליה
אביי דילמא מנודה לשמים שאני דקיל. Amar lei Abaye dilma menudeh lashamayim
shani dekil. Oh, maybe that's different, maybe that's more lenient. קיל? Kil?
Lenient? אמרת חמור Amarta chamur earlier you said it was more weighty.
ספקי מספקא ליה, Speiki mesapka lei,
so he doesn't know whether it's more weighty or more lenient. ומדחי
ליה, Umidachi lei, and he pushes off either way. Now of course
this is bizarre because this בשילוח קרבנותיו bishale'ach korbanosav is all about
your relationship to God. So it's one thing to say that מנודה
לבריות menudeh labriyos is more חמור chamur in the practices that are
about you being, you know, expressing your rejection from society. But here
we're suggesting that in terms of the הלכה halakha of bringing קרבנות,
korbanos, it's worse to be מנודה לבריות menudeh labriyos than it is
to be מנודה לשמים, menudeh lashamayim, right? Which is very bizarre. קרבנות
Korbanos seems to be all about your relationship to God, again, unless
you say that, you know, sort of like, you know, that bringing
קרבנות korbanos was very much the public sort of, you know, religious
communal type of practice. I mean imagine, you know, going to the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and not your own little private במה bamah
in your backyard. Right? So even though you're משלח קרבנותיו, meshale'ach korbanosav,
there's a very public sort of participatory aspect to being משלח קרבן.
meshale'ach korban. It's very, but again, very strange that the גמרא, Gemara
even with that said, suggests that מנודה לשמים menudeh lashamayim is more
lenient in that way than מנודה לבריות. menudeh labriyos. How about a
מצורע? metzora So the גמרא Gemara says, ומצורע מהו שישלח קרבנותיו? umetzora
mahu sheyishale'ach korbanosav? How about a מצורע? metzora So תא שמע, Ta
shema, come and hear, דתני תנא ברייתא, detani tana baraisa, ואחרי טהרתו,
ve-acharei taharaso, and this is a פסוק pasuk by יחזקאל, Yechezkel, you
know,
about after somebody became טמא tamei then they'll bring their קרבנות. korbanos.
So אחרי פרישתו מן המת. acharei prishaso min hameis. So the first
part of the פסוק pasuk is talking about after the person is
no longer encountering dead bodies. שבעת ימים, shivas yamim, going back to
the פסוק, pasuk, יספרו לו, yisperu lo, count seven days. This is
all explicating a verse in יחזקאל. Yechezkel אלו זיין ימי ספירה. elu
zayin yemei sphiroso. So that extra point about counting seven days, that
now comes to incorporate the idea of a מצורע Metzora, who has
seven days of counting. וביום באו אל הקודש אל החצר הפנימית לשרת
בקודש יקריב חטאתו. Uveyom bo el hakodesh el hachatzer hapnimis leshareis bakodesh
yakriv chataso. And this is talking about a כהן, kohen, when he
comes to the holy, to the inner sanctuary in order to serve
he shall bring his sin offering. Top of ס"ז ע"א. samech zayin
amud aleph. זו עשירית האיפה שלו, Zu asiris haeifah shelo, read דברי
רבי יהודה. dibrei Rabbi Yehuda. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says that has
nothing to do with being טמא, tamei, that's just the general rule
that a כהן kohen brings a tenth of an איפה eifah to
sort of initiate him in his service as a כהן. kohen. רבי
שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says no, it's
not talking about a כהן, kohen, it's talking about a normal person,
and only after he becomes טהור tahor from being a מצורע Metzora
can he then bring a קרבן. korban. Because the end of the
verse is ובבואו יקריב, ve-uvo yakriv, when he comes he shall bring,
בזמן שראוי לביאה ראוי להקרבה, bizman sheraui levi'ah raui le-hakravah, when he's
able to enter in, that's when he can bring his קרבנות. korbanos.
בזמן שאינו ראוי לביאה, bizman she-eino raui levi'ah, if he can't himself
enter in because he's a מצורע, Metzora, אינו ראוי להקרבה, eino raui
le-hakravah, he cannot bring. Now, so it's sort of the way תוספות
Tosfos reads this, this is a debate between רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
and רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda doesn't read this
about a מצורע Metzora not being able to bring, but רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon does. Now again, it should be recognized this is not
a general rule. The general rule is that טמא משלח קרבנותיו. tamei
meshale'ach korbanosav. Somebody who is טמא tamei can send his קרבנות korbanos
to be brought for him. So this is specifically a הלכה halakha
by a מצורע although it is framed in a more general sense.
Okay. So is משלח קרבנותיו, meshale'ach korbanosav, which side of the equation
is this? It sounds more, you know, okay, this might be a
debate, but it sounded more that the evidence was that they did
it in the מדבר midbar and that it really is only for
an
אבל אינו משלח קרבנותיו. eino meshale'ach korbanosav. Okay. But again the גמרא
Gemara is not clear about that and that might be one of
these things that it's also clear as well. So there's a whole
range of things where it's not clear which way it sides. And
some of these things we can put into the sort of communal
societal. The שילוח קרבנות shiluach korbanos we just said. The ניעיל הסנדל
niggal hasandah we said. The... that was suggested yesterday has a very
communal aspect of it. But the one thing, so these things are
sort of questionable which side they go on, you know, and these
could be more about like, you know, this could be more like
the תורה and the affirmative aspect of it and these could be
about a sense of צער Tza'ar which is not as, you know,
not as relevant to this. But the one thing as I said
that to me still sort of problematizes this, this division, is the
תשמיש המטה. Tashmish HaMittah. First you had a question. No, no. Okay,
Charlie, yeah.
So, this verse from יחזקאל, Yechezkel how can we take יחזקאל Yechezkel
for a...
Yeah! We were learning all of some of this stuff before and,
you know, and so a lot of these things you have to
recognize, by the way, are anyway, are rabbinic. The whole institution of
נידוי Niddui, is not a biblical institution, number one. Although here it's
about an issue about מצורע, that's true. אבילות Aveilus other than the
first day everybody agrees is rabbinic. But to the degree that like
we're trying to learn this out for something about a מצורע and
trying to affirm that this is a דאורייתא De'oraita practice of מצורע,
because even though מצורע is דאורייתא, De'oraita, is this practice, משלוח קרבנות
Mishloach Korbanot is not clear. You know, the גמרא Gemara doesn't question
it here, it questions it elsewhere and it says, so before יחזקאל
Yechezkel came along, how did we know it? And it says, oh,
it must have been a מסורה Masorah and יחזקאל Yechezkel came and
gave us a פסוק. Pasuk. So it is true, the גמרא Gemara
elsewhere questions learning from יחזקאל and basically says, fine, we're not really
learning, we knew it anyway, it's just the evidence is in...
A couple verses earlier, יחזקאל says that a כהן Kohen can't marry...
I understand, well that's why the גמרא Gemara said they wanted to
be גנוז ספר יחזקאל. Ganuz Sefer Yechezkel. Why does it mention חטאת?
Chatat? I don't know. All right, we're going to move on. Now
that is... now we are done with the list, David. Now we're
done with the list, so these are all of the things as
I said, there's I think a general understanding of what are the
areas of similarity and what are the areas of difference, but it,
you know, whether it works 100 percent is questionable. Yes. Why, what?
Wine? Wine and meat.
That's right, so that's specifically for אונן, Onein, so you are right
that the גמרא Gemara has before quoted things about אונן, Onein, you
know, and it really was more about אבילות, Aveilus, some of these
phrases were about אונן, Onein, you know, but it, or not doing
מצוות. Mitzvot. So the גמרא Gemara is not really looking at אונן,
Onein, it's really looking at אבל, even though sometimes it uses the
phrase אונן, Onein, sometimes that phrase did refer also to practices of
אבילות. Aveilus. There's in general a fascinating debate in the ראשונים Rishonim
whether אנינות Aninus and אבילות Aveilus are fundamentally two
distinct practices, which is I think how we understand them, or whether
to see them as one type of a continuum. Okay, but for
now we're just going to acknowledge that the גמרא Gemara is focused
on אבילות Aveilus practices even though it references אונן, Onein, you know,
and not something that's basically an אונן Onein practice. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara now continues in the following.
Let's take a look.
Now we get, so that's the end of the practices and now
the rest of the דף, in addition to certain אגדתות Aggadot are
going to be focused on what,
how somebody gets to be a
מנודה. Classic examples of becoming of why you would impose נידוי, niduy.
so let's take a look. So אמר רבא, Amar Rava, says רבא,
Rava, מנלן דמשדרינן שליחא דבי דינא ומזמנינן ליה לדינא. minalan de'meshadrinan shlicha
de'bei dina mezamnan leih le'dina. How do we know that you send
a messenger of the court in order to call somebody to court?
Basically to issue like a subpoena, a summons, right, a summons. A
subpoena is for evidence, right? No, what is it when somebody has
to appear because they're being... a summons. Okay. How do we know
you send a messenger and issue a summons? דכתיב, De'chtiv, וישלח משה
לקרא לדתן ולאבירם בני אליאב. vayishlach Moshe likro le'Datan vela'Aviram bnei Eliav.
Okay. ומנלן דמזמנינן לדינא? U'minalan de'mezamnan le'dina? משה Moshe sent
and said to them you guys got to appear and we're going
to discuss this. ומנלן דמזמנינן לדינא? U'minalan de'mezamnan le'dina? Now they
sort of ask the question again, but we'll see he's going to
now elaborate on it. So and how do we know that you
call the, you know, the litigants or whatever, the people that are
being charged? דכתיב, De'chtiv, ויאמר משה אל קרח אתה וכל עדתך. vayomer
Moshe el Korach atah ve'chol adatcha. Okay,
you and all your congregation. So so far it said the same
thing, but now it continues other points that we learn from this.
לקמי גברא רבא. Likmi gavra raba. How do we know that the
summons says, appear before this great person, meaning appear before so and
so the judge, that you mention who the appearance is before, who
is sort of the judge of the case? דכתיב, De'chtiv, because the
next line, section of the verse says, לפני השם. lifnei Hashem. Okay,
so appear before God. So not necessarily... so anyway but
the judges though, you know, it goes back to also the rabbinic
idea that אלוהים, Elohim, especially in פרשת משפטים, Parshat Mishpatim, refers to
judges, judges are sort of, you know, representing God's law. So anyway,
that's how we learn it out, but who you are being called
to appear before. So the summons would say who you're being called
to appear before, so and so's court. אתה ופלניא. Atah u'planya. Now
how do we know the summons says you and so and so,
meaning it mentions who the other person in the case is in
the summons? דכתיב, De'chtiv, אתה והם ואהרן, atah ve'heim ve'Aharon, you and
they and אהרן. Aharon.
So this is what a summons would say: you, so and so,
must appear before the court of the, you know, the great judge
so and so, you and and that would mention who your, who
you know, who your antagonist is, who the person who you're going
up against in the court is. Now, דכתבינן זימנא, dekhavinan zimna, how
do you know that you give the person a period of time
to show up, you know, come at this date? דכתיב, dekhtiv, מחר,
machar,
appear tomorrow. זימנא בתר זימנא, zimna batar zimna, how do you know
that if they don't appear at the first summons that you issue
a second summons and give them a second opportunity for a court
date before there's going to be consequences to their non-appearance? דכתיב, dekhtiv,
קראו שם פרעה מלך מצרים
שאון העביר המועד. karu sham paroh melekh mitsrayim shaon he-evir hamo-ed. So
you know, there, so, so Rashi reads that the word שם sham
here, I forgot, I didn't look it up if maybe the, maybe
the, the vocalization is שם shem or שם, sham, but anyway Rashi
reads it as שמתא, shamta, as a which is the Aramaic expression
for נידוי. niduy, So actually, you know, reading that give, declare for
him a נידוי, niduy? an excommunication. What word were we using yesterday
for
נידוי? niduy, Ostracism because he has passed the right time. So but
anyway it means that he, after you allow it, you know, so
after one miss, you know, there's another calling out. But it's interesting
because the שמתא shamta isn't after the first time he's passed, it's
only after he missed twice. Anyway somehow it's learning from that that
there's another, that there's another summons that follows the first. Okay. ומנלן...
u-menalan... okay, so ומנלן דאי מספקר
בשליחא דבי דינא, u-menalan de-i mispaker bi-shlikha de-vei dina,
how do you
know that if he acts, you know,
in a disparaging way, in a disrespectful way? And the word is
מספקר mispaker which is the same word as אפיקורוס. apikores. And I
should remind you by the way that the גמרא Gemara in סנהדרין,
Sanhedrin, you know, on the famous משנה mishnah that an אפיקורוס apikores
doesn't have a portion in the world to come, says an אפיקורוס
apikores is somebody who acts disparagingly to תלמידי חכמים. talmidei chakhamim. The
גמרא Gemara very much understands that the idea of and the, you
know, that the idea of recognizing, not just honoring the sages, but
accepting their status and the sort of rabbinic authority that they represent
obviously is very central to the well running of society guided by,
you know, guided by religious law and represented by the sages. People
need to recognize their authority and to act appropriately towards them or
it deeply undermines. We're just about to enter into פרשת שופטים, Parashat
Shoftim, you know, one of the big things in שופטים Shoftim and
that started already in ראה Re-eh is challenges to the basic institutions
of society. And what do you do when people challenge the basic
institutions of society? In these last two פרשיות, parshiyot, you kill 'em,
right? So that's the בן סורר ומורה, ben sorer u-moreh, that's the
זקן ממרא, zaken mamre, that's the נביא שקר. navi sheker. Okay, so
the idea here is very important that people give, you know, don't
act in a like in a casting off the yoke way, which
is the, you know, and not just towards, towards the rabbinic authority.
So and that's here represented by the person that's the messenger of
the court. So ומנלן דאי מספקר בשליחא דבי דינא, u-menalan de-i mispaker
bi-shlikha de-vei dina, how do you know if somebody acts in a
sort of a disparaging way
and more than just disrespectful, disrespectful and disparaging towards the messenger of
the court?
דאתי ואמר לא מיתחזי כלישנא בישא, de-ati ve-amar lo mit-chazi ke-lishna bisha,
and then the messenger of the court comes back to us and
says, and tells us what this guy
said, it doesn't appear like לישנא בישא. lishna bisha. He's allowed to
report on how he was treated. דכתיב, dekhtiv, העיני האנשים ההם תנקר
לא נעלה. ha-einei ha-anashim ha-hem tenaker lo na-aleh.
Because by the משה Moshe story you heard what דתן ואבירם Datan
ve-Aviram responded. How did משה Moshe find out what they responded? It
must be the messenger brought that message back, but implicit in that
is that he completely, you know, sort of rejected
me and sort of mocked, you know, mocked me. So therefore you
see that you're allowed to report back. ומנלן דמשמתינן, u-menalan de-meshamtinan,
and now we get to the punchline. How do you know that
you would put this person in שמתא, shamta, in נידוי, niduy? ostracization,
presumably if he acts in this way of
disparagingly towards the messenger of the court, or if he refuses after
two summons to show up to the court, how do you know
you would put him in נידוי? niduy דכתיב, dekhtiv, אורו מרוז, oru
meroz, okay, which is from the whole שירת דבורה, shirat Devorah, and
it is being read as, right, אורו oru like ארור, arur, and
מרוז meroz we'll see is the name of a person. So he
is being sort of cursed for not showing up to the war.
So they're making some type of a comparison. He was called to
be part of the war, he didn't show up, he's being cursed.
You're called to appear to the court, you don't show up, you're
going to be cursed. Or if it's not just passively not showing
up, even worse if you do it in a way which completely
sort of acts disparagingly towards our summons, that's even worse and that
demands an immediate response.
I was missing this: they put Pharaoh in excommunication because he missed
the time and it seemed that you only get one chance. How
are you getting the two chances?
Yeah, so I didn't get that, I didn't get that for the,
that's why I said for the. Yeah, so I didn't get that,
I didn't get that for the רבנו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom who reads
the שם sham as שמתא. shamta. I just read it, so if
you don't read it as שמתא, shamta, you ignore that explanation, it's
just call him again. העביר מועד, He'evir mo'ed, and you call him
again. קראו, Kir'u, so call him, because he's missed his first time.
Call him a second time. All right. So anyway, after certain degree
of non-compliance and certainly of sort of of, you know, actually that
would be a good parallel in, you know, our system, contempt of
court, right, that's actually probably better word for אפקירותא afkeiruta being מפקיר
בשליחא דבי דינא. mafkir bishlicha d'vei dina. That's exactly that. That's what
the word contempt really embodies. It's like you don't treat respectfully because
it's showing that you reject their authority, like you don't recognize the
seriousness of their authority. So that's actually like the perfect word here.
So that contempt of court or non-appearance gets this type of a
response. Okay. Now דהכי סברא דגברא, Dehachi sevara degavra, and then
how do you know in your issuing of the נידוי niduy you
say, you know, you are now being put in contempt or in
נידוי niduy in because of of ostracization because and this is the
opinion of the great judge so and so? You mention the person
who's placing you in contempt. דכתיב Dechtiv because it says אמר מלאך
השם Amar malach Hashem by that verse by by שופטים Shoftim that
was the curse was given by the angel of God, so you
say who is issuing it. ומנלן דמחרמינן? Umenalan demachraminan?
How do you know that you would actually, if it got worse,
put him in חרם, cherem, because that's going to be the next
stage after נידוי niduy. doesn't work? חרם Cherem is more complete, sort
of real, you know, excommunication. דכתיב אורו ארור, Dechtiv oru arur, cursed,
you know,
cursed in double language of cursed, so that's a follow-up if the
first one doesn't work. Now דאכיל ושתי בהדיה וקאי בארבע אמות דידיה.
De'achil veshatei behadeih veka'ei bearba amot dideih.
How do you know that that it apply that you're not allowed
to eat and drink with him and stand within his ארבע אמות?
arba amot? דכתיב יושביה, Dechtiv yosheveiha, right? אורו ארור יושביה. Oru arur
yosheveiha.
So that you're not even allowed to be sitting together with such
a person. ומנלן דפרטינן חטאיה? Umenalan defartinan chata'ei?
How do you know that you enumerate his sins, why he's being
put in this state? בציבורא? Betzibura? You do it publicly. דכתיב כי
לא באו לעזרת השם בגיבורים. Dechtiv ki lo ba'u le'ezrat Hashem bagiborim.
So you know, so you're like announcing why is why is this
person, you know, this מרוז Meroz in this state? דאמר עולא בארבע
מאה
שיפורי שמתיה ברק למרוז. De'amar Ulla bearba mei'a shipurei shamteih Barak leMeroz.
With 400 שופרות, shofrot, right? So here it's clear that when they
put somebody in חרם cherem they did it by blowing the שופר
shofar and they did it so again it's an exaggeration, but whatever
they made a major announcement when he put him in in נידוי.
niduy איכא דאמרי Ika de'amri it says it was Barak who did
it by the way not דבורה Devorah in case you were worried.
Okay so איכא דאמרי Ika de'amri others say גברא רבא הוה. Gavra
raba hava. Now who was this מרוז? Meroz? Some say he was
a great person and he did not participate in the war and
that was a terrible thing to hold back. ואיכא דאמרי כוכבא הוה.
Ve'ika de'amri kochava hava. It was a star that the stars, as
we're going to see, you know, participated in bringing about the downfall
of סיסרא Sisera and one star refused.
שנאמר מן שמים נלחמו הכוכבים. Shene'emar min shamayim nilchamu hakochavim. Okay. ומנלן
דמפקרינן נכסיה? Umenalan demaphkerinan nichsei? How do you know that as a
next stage one of the tools at your disposal is that you
can actually make his property, you can seize his property, make it
הפקר hefker and allow people to take his property, you know, if
just being cast out of society isn't enough, let's try to hit
him in the, you know, you know in his wallet. דכתיב Dechtiv
it says וכל אשר לא יבוא. Vechol asher lo yavo. We're going
to use a different model not by not by the whole שירת
דבורה shirat Devorah but by עזרא Ezra where it's very and this
model very much is the one that's used for the principle of
הפקר בית דין הפקר hefker beit din hefker that when they were
trying to, you know, actually institute some societal reforms that they have
a consequence that your property will be made ownerless if you do
not comply. So that is a, you know, that's a tool that's
available to be used. So
דכתיב וכל אשר לא יבוא לשלשת הימים בעצת השרים והזקנים Dechtiv vechol
asher lo yavo lishloshet hayamim ba'atzat hasarim vehazekenim anybody who doesn't come
within three days in the advice of the officers and the elders,
יחרם כל רכושו yochoram kol rechusho will all of his property be
put in חרם. cherem. So by the way notice the same word
חרם cherem here which is actually in the תורה which applies to
property, right?
מכל אשר יחרם מן האדם מן הבהמה לא יפדה יומת Mikol asher
yochoram min ha'adam min habehema lo yipadeh yumat right applies to a
status put on like presumably, you know, making something off limits but
here it's off limits to the
person, right? You know חרם cherem was עכן Achan use the phrase
חרם cherem as well right because he was מועל בחרם. mo'el bacherem.
So חרם cherem could mean off limits to everyone, taboo and is
destroyed, but here the same idea being used that you, if it's
forbidden to you, it's taken away from you and it's made free
for others, which is not explicit in the פסוק. pasuk. But again
notice by the way the similarity of חרם cherem of the property
and the person being put in חרם cherem being off limits. Okay,
so יחרם כל רכושו והוא יבדל מקהל הגולה yochoram kol rechusho vehu
yibadel mikahal hagola and he will be cast out and here's the
cast out or separated from the community right, so from so so
there you have this combination of this idea of חרם cherem of
the person cast
out. So ומנלן u'minalan דנצינן d'natzinan
and how do you know that such a person we would argue
with, fight with, וליטנן v'litnan and curse, ומכנין u'machinan we would hit,
ותלשינן v'talsinan hair we pull his hair, that's pretty
interesting, okay, ומשביעינן u'mashbi'inan and we would and we would and we
would make him you know so we would we would swear him
in an
oath, דכתיב d'chtiv ואריב עמם va'ariv imam and I fought with them,
this is again by the stories of Ezra נחמיה, Nechemya, ואקללם va'akalalem
and I cursed them, ואכה מהם va'akeh mehem and I had to
smite some of them, אנשים anashim ואמרטם va'emretem and I pulled their
hair, ואשביעם va'ashbi'em and I you know and I made them and
I made them swear an oath. So basically you can use whatever
devices are necessary. But again this is quite different than just this
idea, you know this is just based in using force. This is
a very different type of a thing. Until now we were using
societal, you know, pressure devices and so on and even sort of
taking property we're going to different levels. One is sort of ostracization
from society, the other is seizing the property, the other is actually
corporal, you know, bodily force.
Okay, ומנלן דכפתינן u'minalan d'kaftinan and talking about that, how do you
know that some people if necessary you can bind them, ואסרינן v'asrinan
and we basically we bind them to a post, to a whipping
post, ועבדינן הרדפה v'avdinan hardafah and we do הרדפה, hardafah, what's we'll
see what
הרדפה hardafah is, דכתיב d'chtiv הן למות הן לשרשו, hen l'maves hen
l'shashu, whether to death, so said how do you know you can
put them to death if you need to, whether לשרשו shashu which
we'll see what that means, הן לענש נכסין hen l'onash nechasin whether
to to punish them in their property, which is the seizing of
the property we said before, ולאסורין v'la'asurin and to like be bound.
So how do you move to death, as it didn't appear for
a bodily, I mean for a monetary?
How do you know basically the court can do what the court
needs to do?
So that's you know that's special emergency practice, yeah, like pay your
parking ticket.
Exactly. מאי לשרושי? Mai l'shashu? It doesn't spell out under what circumstances,
but look, we have gone from a discussion of חרם cherem to
a basic discussion of powers of the sort of the court, which
is the sort of both religious and and judicial, you know, it's
very relevant to שופטים, Shoftim, it's both the religious and the judicial
authority. So how do we know that these are all the powers
that a court has available to it, we're no longer just talking
about חרם. cherem.
All right, so מאי לשרושי, mai l'shashu, what does לשרושי l'shashu mean?
The גמרא Gemara says אמר אדא מרי אמר נחמיה בר ברוך אמר
רב חייא בר אבין אמר רב יהודה הרדפה. Amar Adda Mari amar
Nechemya bar Baruch amar Rav Chiya bar Avin amar Rav Yehuda Hardafah.
So that's what we said before, that you could do הרדפה. hardafah.
Well that helps. מאי הרדפה? Mai hardafah? So what's הרדפה? hardafah? אמר
רב יהודה בריה דרב שמואל בר שילת משמיה דרב מנדין לאלתר. Amar
Rav Yehuda brei d'Rav Shmuel bar Shilas mishmei d'Rav menadin l'altar. It
means when necessary you can put the guy in נידוי niduy. immediately,
you don't have to go through like a process if you feel
it necessary you can immediately impose נידוי.
Nidui It can be a special court, it can't be like your
regular garden variety three people or getting together for a בית דין
beis din that they can like go kill somebody.
Yeah it's not clear, I mean you know that gets into the
whole issue בית דין מכין ועונשין שלא מן הדין, beis din makin
v'onshin shelo min hadin, right? So that doesn't mean that it's part
of this is sort of extra-legal you know sort of things that
are measured used in in
emergency circumstances, you know when the שעתה צריכה להם. sha'ata tzricha lahem.
That's the idea that חז"ל Chazal have, whether how much was it
really practiced I don't know, but we're not talking about about like
the beginning of סנהדרין Sanhedrin that you need twenty-three you know to
impose a חיוב מיתה. chiyuv misah. It's not a חיוב מיתה, chiyuv
misah, it's because they're also sort of they're also like the police,
they're not just the בית דין beis din you know, so this
is more in their policing controlling society function. Just a court system?
Exactly, yes.
I'm thinking of ריטב"א Ritva here, so do you think that this
is what they use as a justification for for using כפינן? kafinan?
Yeah, I mean I think I'm not yes right, I mean I
think that more draws on the discussions in גיטין Gittin where it
speaks specifically about כפינן kafinan that you can physically force somebody to
give a גט, get, but you know but that is part of
the larger picture of the powers of בית דין, beis din, yes,
but there's a specific discussion about them in the גט get context,
yes.
But that passage from נחמיה Nechemya is actually the last historical event
in נ"ך. Nach. Oh interesting. After all after all that stuff they're
still marrying foreign wives and there
was depending on whether the story of אסתר Esther happened before or
after that, right?
But basically we have all these remedies. Yes. For contempt of court,
contempt of society, contempt of whatever. Right. If
they
you say they can seize his property? Yes and use the proceeds
for what? What what are you supposed to remedy? Right. And how
does the person come back into a state of grace?
Well, I mean you could say after somebody's also been given lashes,
how do they come I mean some things are not as reversible
as others, but I don't understand why I mean don't wouldn't you
think that like better to if you're going to try to impose
sanctions better for it to first do you know monetary sanctions before
you have to do more violent ones?
I think the most extreme that
we
have...
I mean, right, you'd rather have a speeding ticket than be thrown
in jail, right? You'd rather get thrown in jail than, I mean,
there's degrees. So, I mean, that's why נידוי Nidui, is the most
נידוי, Nidui I mean, which, you know, is the most,
like, like lenient almost of the things, you know, because it is,
like, you start some practices, it doesn't have lasting impact, it's reversible
once you start doing the right types of things. These other things
are a little bit more lasting, right?
It's really about the authority of the court. Absolutely, it's less about
the,
the person.
Right, right. We've switched from a discussion about נידוי Nidui to a
much larger discussion, like שופטים ושוטרים. Shoftim veShotrim. This is like the
שוטרים Shotrim part, you know, the things you do when you want
to compel people to, you know, act in a certain way. Yeah,
it's, it's the society of the court. But, but you know, again,
in חז"ל, Chazal, court and political leadership are conflated a lot, you
know? So this is not exactly, you know, when they call in
the National Guard and when they call in, you know, the, the
troops or the police or whatever, you don't think the courts are
calling them in. But this would be the בית דין. Beis Din.
Yeah, the courts are the rabbis.
Right.
Yeah, the rabbinic authority, the court authority, and the political authority are
all being conflated into this concept called בית דין. Beis Din. That's
true, and that's why maybe some of this is a little bit
confusing because we would never say the court would impose these types
of things. Right, but if you think about, like, you know, what
is it, like,
but we do think that the court imposes sanctions upon you doing
the following.
Sanctions, yeah.
In America, you're right. In America, in other words, the governor calls
in the National Guard to go onto a college campus, the question
is is it legal or not and you go to court, so
we kind of separate. This is all one central authority.
But the marshal, I, I believe operates under the authority of the
court when you,
for
example, throw a tenant out of his, out of his space, you
enforce a contract, the court makes an order and then the marshal
goes out with the authority.
Right. When you hear about, like, you know, how, I'm probably, you
know, colonial America or whatever, you know, where they would do this,
they take the person to the town square, they put them in
the stockades or they, you know, the whipping post or these types
of things. Was that seen as, like, a judicial process or was
that seen as something done by, like, the town elders? I have
no idea.
Well, you have to remember in pre-Colonial America there is no difference
between the church and the state. Aha.
Yeah, I think that's what we're talking about.
You were lucky if you got put in the stocks, they would
be more likely they would give you a certain amount of... they'd
give you a certain amount of time to leave, if you didn't,
they'd kill you.
Okay. So anyway, so this is what we're talking about. So now
we'll continue. The גמרא Gemara says like this. All right,
let's continue. Okay.
ושונין לה אתונא מנדין לאלתר ושונין לאחר ל'. Veshonin lah atuna mendin
le'altar veshonin le'achar lamed.
So now here's the, by the way, a preface. You put somebody,
you put somebody in נידוי Nidui right away. If that person doesn't
begin to comply, doesn't comply, you repeat the נידוי Nidui, for another
thirty-day period. Meaning, there's a certain amount of time. Yes. But if
you don't comply, you get it again, and if you don't comply
twice, then ומחרימין לאחר ששים. Umachrimim le'achar shishim.
So after two periods of נידוי, Nidui, after sixty days, then the
person's in חרם. Cherem. So, you know, keep on, keep on upping
the, you know, increasing the sanctions if the person does not comply.
אמר ליה רב הונא בר חיננא הכי אמר רב חסדא. Amar lei
Rav Huna bar Chinana hachi amar Rav Chisda. This is what Rav
Chisda says: מזהרין בשני וחמישי ושני. Maz'harin be-Sheni va-Chamishi ve-Sheni. You warn
him
Monday, Thursday, Monday, which could mean two things. It could mean, or
actually, as a פשט, pshat, is that before you apply the first
נידוי, Nidui. you give him a Monday, Thursday, Monday of warning to
get his, you know, to start complying before you impose the sanctions,
and then you impose the first נידוי. Nidui Others want to say
that this is being more strict and saying that the first נידוי
Nidui. applies for like Monday, Thursday, Monday and then you move right
into חרם. Cherem. So not thirty days. Yeah, that he's being much
more strict than the previous set. I don't see it. I see
it saying you first have a period of warning, then you have
sanction number one, then sanction number two, and then you've
got חרם. Cherem. Okay. So הני מילי לממונא. Hani milei lemamona. And
that's when the problem, the reason you're applying these sanctions, now we're,
now we're sort of away from all this physical stuff and we're
back to נידוי. Nidui Okay. And that's when the reason you're applying
this נידוי nidui, is because of certain types of civil issues, like,
you know, he's not showing up to a court case, somebody is
suing him or whatever and he's, you know, refusing to show up.
So then you do that. אבל לאפקירותא, Aval le'afkiroosa, if it's about
contempt of the rabbis, contempt of court, לאלתר, le'altar, then you don't
give him a Monday, Thursday, Monday. You start imposing it right away.
And now we're going to have some stories. Okay. ההוא טבחא, Hahu
tabacha, there was a certain butcher דאישתפקא de'ishtapkha that acted with contempt
ברבי טובי בר מתנא. be-Rabbi Tuvi bar Masna. Rabbi Tuvi bar Masna.
And again, presumably this doesn't just mean like, you know, didn't stand
up when he walked into the room, it means in a way
that can really rejected, you know, his authority.
Okay. שמעו ביה אביי ורבא, Shamu beih Abaye ve'Rava, so Abaye and
Rava made a בית דין Beis Din ושמתוה, v'shamtuh, and they put
him in חרם cherem in נידוי, nidui? okay, which is how you
respond to that type of
behavior. And so, אזל פייסיה לבעל דיניה. azal piseih le'baal dineih. Then
he went and he, you know, and he made up with his,
with the person he was fighting with. Now it's interesting, he should
be making up with Rav Tuvi bar Mattana. So maybe, you know,
maybe that's what it means, but it sounds more like he and
his other, you know, he and the person that he was having
this court case with, his litigant, were in front of Rav Tuvi
bar Mattana and he acted in a contemptuous way in that case
of the court. And now he's made up with his litigant, but,
you know, part of that story has to be but you also
presumably have to, you know, ask forgiveness from Rav Tuvi bar Mattana.
So presumably that's what it means, although it's not so black and
white. Anyway, so he, but but here he was, he conformed his
behavior appropriately.
אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, היכי לעביד? Heichi le'avid? What should we do?
לישרי ליה? Lishrei leih? Should we now release him from his state
of נידוי? nidui לא חל שמתא לתלתין יומין. Lo chal shamta le'talsin
yomin. It was not thirty days, and we understand a נידוי nidui
period is thirty days. Maybe you have to suffer the, you know,
the punishment even after you've, you know,
conformed. You'll conform so you won't get, it won't be extended, but
maybe the full weight of your action has to be punished and
has to be a full thirty days. לא לישרי ליה? Lo lishrei
leih? Should we not release him? קא בעו רבנן למיעל. Ka ba'u
rabanan le'me'el. The Rabbis have to, want to go up. Now, what
does go up mean? So Rabbeinu Gershom says like somehow they needed
this person and they needed him to help them do something. Anyway,
the גירסא girsa which is the גירסא girsa says to למיפק. le'mifak.
The Rabbis need to leave or למיזל, le'meizal, excuse me, which means
that the בית דין, Beis Din, and this works with the continuation
of the discussion, the בית דין Beis Din that put him in
חרם, cherem, people are now leaving, we're disbanding. People want to go
home, whatever, maybe they were gathered together for a weekend and this
guy conformed and now everybody wants to go home. Should we have
to wait thirty days? We're not gonna be able to reconstitute the
בית דין. Beis Din. People are traveling. So maybe we should do
it right now. So
אמר ליה לרב אידי בר אבין, Amar leih le'Rav Idi bar Avin,
so they said to
Rav Idi bar
Avin, מיני שמיע לך בהא? Mini shemia lach be'ha? Have you heard
a ruling about this, about whether we can, we can release somebody
from his נידוי nidui, right away? So אמר ליה, Amar leih, so
he said, הכי אמר רב תחליפא בר אבין אמר שמואל, Hachi amar
Rav Tachlifa bar Avin amar Shmuel, this is what was said. תות
אסר ותות שרי. Tut asar ve'tut sharei. So this means, the way
it's normally explained is, it's funny, the onomatopoeia, תות, tut, which basically
means the blowing of the שופר, shofar, okay? So the blowing of
the שופר shofar made him forbid, you know, created the, the restrictions,
and the blowing of the שופר shofar will release him. So the
same way we could, we could act to, to bind, to impose
the נידוי, nidui we could act right away to release him if
we see fit. So אמר ליה, Amar leih, one minute, הני מילי
ממונא. Hani mili mamona. That I know, but that's true when it's
an issue of civil dispute and the guy isn't showing up, let's
say, to the בית דין Beis Din or other things such as
that
nature. אבל אפקירותא, Aval afkeiruta, but when it's a real issue of
contempt, עד דחייל שמתא לתלתין יומין. Ad de'chayel shamta le'talsin yomin. Maybe
you need it to be a full thirty days. So that's the
issue, and it was not really resolved because a contempt is a
worse thing, maybe it needs to be fully punished. So anyway, so
it wasn't resolved, but now the גמרא says whether you can release
somebody from that, from when he was put in חרם, cherem, when
he was put in נידוי nidui, because of contempt, if you can
release him right away. Anyway, now the גמרא says אמר קסבר אביי,
Amar kasavar Abaye, we see implicit in this
that Abaye holds, הני בי תלתא דשמיתו, Hani be talsah de'shamitu, לא
אתו תלתא אחריני ושרו ליה, lo atu talsah achrinei ve'sharu leih, that
the three that put the person in חרם cherem or a נידוי,
nidui, another בית דין Beis Din cannot release him. Because the whole
story was, he felt an urgency to do it right away because
the court was going to disband and people were going to leave.
So you see he felt that you needed the same court that,
to release him, to be the same court that put him in
that state to be the one that released him.
Where were we? Okay, דאיבעיא לן, De'ibaya lan, because we've raised this
question, הני בי תלתא דשמיתו, Hani be talsah de'shamitu, three people that
put somebody in נידוי, nidui מהו למיתי תלתא אחריני ושרו ליה? mahu
le'meisi talsah achrinei ve'sharu leih? Can a different בית דין Beis Din
release him? So that you could understand would be a bit of
a challenge because then, you know, just find three people that are
sympathetic to you and nobody has any authority, okay? So maybe let's
say it means can they do it maybe not against the, you
know, if it's not opposing the authority of the original three, but
can another three be at least the body to release him? But
it obviously would raise serious questions under what circumstances. Okay, so תא
שמע, come and hear. נידויה דרב נידויה דתלמיד. Niduya de'Rav niduya de'talmid.
If somebody is in a state of נידוי nidui to the, to
the master, to the rebbe, he obviously the תלמידים talmidim have to
practice that. Now I need to say that until now we have
been talking about נידוי Nidduy, not as the practice of other people,
but the practice this guy does. Okay, but there is also the
aspect of the practice of other people. And we should, I you
know, we we were rushing through it before, but let's stop and
mention that what the גמרא mentions before is not to eat and
drink with him and not to sit in his ארבע אמות. arba
amos. Now that is a pretty serious form of ostracization. The ironic
thing is is that the person isn't totally cut off because we
said before he can hire laborers, he can be hired out,
he can teach, he can be taught so it's not like no
interaction but at least the sort of communal sense of eating together,
right eating together is a very powerful sense
of being included and community and a sense of like a tight
intimate bond that you don't eat with him and you don't sit
in ארבע אמות—does Arba Amos that sit in ארבע אמות? Arba Amos?
There's actually an interesting question, I'm serious, can you stand in his
ארבע אמות? Arba Amos? Meaning it's one thing to sit with somebody,
right? Sitting with somebody is a more intimate sense. Standing is just
a form of interaction and we did see interactions were allowed. חרם
Cherem you can't have any interaction. You can't do business,
he can't learn from people, he can't teach other people, that's completely
cutting off all interaction. This this is נידוי, Nidduy. which is a
more intimate
kind of interaction so eating and sitting in ארבע אמות Arba Amos
are of a different is one thing but that does not mean
a complete shunning, although in our mind it sounds like that.
Okay so is there why is spouse is also a completely
I don't think so, but I don't remember. So anyway, so punishment
for
violating that for some not being well
that's I think what the גמרא says and what do you do
if the person keeps on violating so we have other means at
our disposal.
But let's say you go and you you're not the מנודה. Right.
You go and you sit down.
Ah, what would what would they do to me if I violated
it? I guess they could decide whether they wanted to put me
in נידוי. Nidduy
Interesting. Possibly.
Yeah, contemptuous it's contemptuous of their
authority in a similar way, that's what they would ask me. Okay,
but anyway, but that is really worth understanding. By the way, the
רמב"ם Rambam says also that somebody who's in נידוי Nidduy can't count
to a מנין. Minyan. Interesting, right? Because that sense of like defining
community, but you know then other פוסקים Poskim sort of speak about
well if there's already a מנין Minyan can he דאוון daven in
the מנין Minyan and the general sense is yes. So again there's
like this tight sense of community, right eating together, counting in a
מנין, Minyan, those things even a מנודה cannot do but interaction is
allowed. Yes.
Is there some place a list of even illustrative of what moves
you into נידוי Nidduy or what moves you from נידוי Nidduy into
yes, so here we had one if you basically you know two
times were in the state of נידוי Nidduy and didn't comply you
would move to חרם. Cherem.
But there's right that's what from doing oh from doing what? So
that's in the רמב"ם. Rambam. So if you're interested in this, the
רמב"ם, Rambam, where's
my phone which is where I have all my ספרים Sfarim on
my
phone, the רמב"ם Rambam I was I'll just do this quickly because
we're running out of time, but the רמב"ם Rambam a good place
if you're interested to see like it brought together a list of
practices and the process or whatever appears in the רמב"ם. Rambam. Any
guesses where it would appear in the רמב"ם? Rambam? If I had
had to guess I would have said in הלכות ממרים Hilchos Mamrim
because that's about authority, but yes do you know? What'd you say?
I think you were right if I heard you הלכות תלמוד תורה,
Hilchos Talmud Torah, believe it or not, because he puts it under
the discussion of כיבוד Kibbud of כבוד רב. Kovod Rav. Oh wow.
Which is fascinating because כבוד רב Kovod Rav again we're thinking more
of like בית דין, Beis Din, political authority, but it's about the
merging of all of these concepts, right about Rabbinic authority. Anyway what?
So in the רמב"ם Rambam it's in הלכות תלמוד תורה Hilchos Talmud
Torah and I'll just read you very quickly I think it's פרק
ה, Perek Hey, is it?
No פרק
yeah it starts in פרק ה. Oh no פרק ו, Perek Vav,
excuse me. So you want to know the list of things that
will get you into חרם? Cherem? Okay here we go. Here's
so the רמב"ם Rambam says like this, על עשרים וארבעה דברים מנדין
את האדם בין איש בין אשה, Al esrim ve-arba devarim menadin es
ha-adam bein ish bein isha,
so there's your equal treatment.
Okay, המבזה את החכם, Hamivazeh es ha-chacham, המבזה שליח בית דין, Hamivazeh
shliach Beis Din, הקורא לחבירו עבד, Hakoreh l'chavero eved, that's interesting right,
that's not about Rabbinic authority.
מי ששלחו לו בית דין וקבעו לו זמן ולא בא,
Mi sheshalchu lo Beis Din
ve-kavu lo zman velo ba, המזלזל בדבר אחד מדברי סופרים ואין צריך
לומר מדברי תורה, Hamizulzel b'davar echad midivrei sofrim ve-ein tzarich lomar midivrei
Torah, so Rabbinic you know you contempt the Torah it's not a
rabbi, right? מזלזל, Mizulzel, doesn't mean over but מזלזל, Mizulzel, right? המזלזל
שליח בית דין Mizulzel shliach Beis Din oh I just
did המזלזל שליח בית דין. Mizulzel shliach Beis Din. מי שלא קיבל
עליו את הדין מנדין אותו עד שיתן, Mi shelo kibel alav es
hadin menadin oso ad sheyiten, doesn't comply with the ruling of the
court. מי שיש
ברשותו דבר המזיק mi sheyesh birshuso davar hamazik and you're not מסיר
mesiro so you have like these mad dog in your property and
you don't do anything about it. המוכר קרקעו לנכרי, Hamocher karkao l'nochri,
that's interesting. המעיד על ישראל בערכאות של נכרים, hame'id al Yisrael b'arkaos
shel nochrim, you go and you take things to secular court and
not Rabbinic court and goes on and on. So it's a list
of 24 things you could see in the רמב"ם Rambam but they're
not all of the same scene, they're not all the same policy.
Okay it's already 8:30 but let's just read to let's just finish
this point let's just read a few more sentences. מנודה לרב מנודה
לתלמיד, Menudah lerav menudah letalmid, so if a רב Rav put somebody
in נידוי Nidduy. the students have to
obviously act in a similar way and treat that person with a
state of
נידוי. Nidduy, מנודה לתלמיד אינו מנודה לרב, Menudah letalmid eino menudah lerav,
but if a תלמיד talmid put him in נידוי, niduy the רב
does not have to. Now it's what It's going to be clear
is that this is when the נידוי niduy is a personal response
because somebody was מזלזל mezalzel was contemptuous of you know their way
of treating me. So that at a personal level I if I'm
a rabbi can put that person in חרם. cherem. And then that's
not like a universal נידוי niduy and other people like you know
people below me have to abide by that practice but people above
me like my רבי Rebbe doesn't have to abide by that practice.
If however somebody is put in נידוי niduy because of a more
not of a personal thing of a personal זלזול בכבוד zilzul b'chavod
but contemptuous of the court system or of other types of practices
then obviously that person is in נידוי niduy. of the whole community.
Okay but that's an interesting new concept being introduced here which is
a more subjective or personal
נידוי. niduy מנודה לרב מנודה לתלמיד מנודה לתלמיד אינו מנודה לרב. Menudeh
l'Rav menudeh l'talmid menudeh l'talmid eino menudeh l'Rav. מנודה לעירו מנודה לעיר
אחרת. Menudeh l'iro menudeh l'ir acheret. So if the city puts him
in נידוי niduy other cities have to comply. מנודה לעיר אחרת אינו
מנודה לעירו Menudeh l'ir acheret eino menudeh l'iro
which is again interesting but you know who knows what makes other
cities respond to the way you know to people from our city
so maybe we don't have to comply by it in our city.
מנודה לנשיא מנודה לכל ישראל Menudeh l'nasi menudeh l'chol Yisrael if the
נשיא nasi put him in נידוי niduy all everybody follows it. מנודה
לכל ישראל אינו מנודה לנשיא Menudeh l'chol Yisrael eino menudeh l'nasi but
not necessarily in the reverse. רבן גמליאל אומר אחד מן התלמידים שנידה
ומת חלקו אינו מופר Rabban Gamliel omer echad min hatalmidim shenidah umes
chelko eino mufar and this is the key line. If one of
the students meaning not a head rabbinic authority but put somebody in
נידוי niduy because he was his you know he was acting treated
contemptuously then after he dies he is no longer available to release
the person from his state which sounds like you need the original
party to release the person from the state. So what does that
mean? שמע מינה תלת Shma mina tlas from this you can infer
three things. שמע מינה תלמיד שנידה לכבודו נידויו נידוי. Shma mina talmid
shenidah l'chvodo niduyo niduy. First of all you hear this idea of
a private נידוי niduy of a personal נידוי niduy that if somebody's
honor was treated with contempt they can do without it being a
broader point they can put that person into נידוי niduy. and it's
more of a personal נידוי. niduy Number one.
And שמע מינה כל אחד ואחד מפר חלקו shma mina kol echad
v'echad mefer chelko that everyone releases their own part and you need
presumably the original person to be there to release them to be
part of the release. And wait wait ושמע מינה הני בי תלתא
דשמיתו לא אתו תלתא אחרינא ושרו ליה u'shma mina hanei bei tlasa
d'shamisu lo asa tlasa achrina v'sharei lei that the original three you
can't have a new three you need presumably the same and each
one has to do you know have to be there for his
part. So it sounds like you need the same people. Maybe that's
only by a personal one maybe if it's a more general one
any body of authority can do it. But anyway the גמרא concludes
this. אמר אמימר הלכתא הני בי תלתא דשמיתו אתו בי תלתא אחרינא
ושרו ליה. Amar Amemar hilchesa hanei bei tlasa d'shamisu asu bei tlasa
achrina v'sharei lei. No a different body can release otherwise the guy
would really be stuck. So the גמרא says אמרי ליה רב אשי
לאמימר והתניא רבן גמליאל אומר אחד מן התלמידים שנידה ומת חלקו אינו
מופר amrei lei Rav Ashi l'Amemar vehatanya Rabban Gamliel omer echad min
hatalmidim shenidah umes chelko eino mufar that if the guy dies he
can his portion of you know is not released. So מאי לאו
אינו מופר כלל mai lav eino mufar klal doesn't it mean that
it's no longer available to release this person? So the גמרא says
לא עד דאתו בי תלתא אחרינא ושרו ליה. lo ad d'asu bei
tlasa achrina v'sharei lei. So until you get another until you constitute
another appropriate body so if the original person isn't around to release
it's not released automatically just because the guy died. You cursed you
were מזלזל mezalzel somebody he died that doesn't free you from your
state. It's not released automatically but you constitute another body and he
can be released which obviously on the one hand seems necessary because
then it's impossible to release somebody. On the other hand then you
have to do with warring authorities. So one בית דין beit din
puts me in חרם cherem it's like what happens now remember you
were invoking Rivka before you know about when a certain community tries
to use sanctions in order to get compliance of giving a גט
get and the guy just goes up in another different community. So
this בית דין beit din puts me in חרם cherem I'll get
another בית דין beit din to release me. Obviously that raises you
know creates a lot of other problems along in its way. Okay
more about נידוי and חרם cherem tomorrow.